sorry I'll repeat so number six the
sixth image is uh
say uh nuk you may have heard Nuku same
thing it means a sprout some it's also
the Tibetan word for bamboo and
therefore became the word for a pen so
when you ask somebody for a pen in the
monastery saying means give me a pen and
the the scriptural word is nuke which
means a sprout some a Sprout coming up
out of the
ground so means
Etc Day means here you know L day which
means Karma and result um so day came to
mean fruit and day here means fruit in
in um Sanskrit it's
Pala which goes into all those words for
f and B and blow and meaning uh expanded
like a fruit okay F comes from
and in Chung means
small and the image here is of I you
know if you've ever visited this
beautiful Orchard uh the image is of an
like an apricot that falls to the ground
and then uh the sun there's sunlight on
it and there's water and then you put
some fertilizer on it and then out of
the small fruit comes a new Sprout for
the next tree so the idea is of
perpetrating uh perpetuating
uh something the the
the the the tree the it's like the the
fruit of the tree becomes the seed for
the next tree
okay Dre meaning normally meaning result
you see so the the full result becomes
the cause for the next tree so the
result becomes a cause you see the fruit
falls down and becomes the seed for the
next tree and then there's this pit or
seed within the fruit okay so that
represents the Buddha nature the flesh
or meat of the fruit uh represents the
veil here and then within it is this the
pit or the seed which represents the
Buddha nature and then from that Buddha
nature comes
what the Sprout which is the Buddha you
see so this would be a good one to use
for what kind of
debate it's Buddha nature and Buddha
hood the yeah nice nice okay cuz in this
one there obviously not not the Sprout
is the buddhahood the Buddha growing and
the seed is the Buddha nature and the
Buddha nature is helping produce the
Sprout because of the
tunkin the conducive conditions of the
sunlight the fertilizer and the rain and
so forth which is a metaphor itself for
tum what's
tum learning learning thinking
meditating on what you've thought about
so you know going to class going home or
driving and thinking about it and then
actually meditating on it okay to some
those three k those three contributing
factors are compared here to the
sunlight and that's the U we said there'
always be well we said often times
there's a something that wakens you up
to the nature to the Buddha nature
that's it that's what it is in this case
okay something that helps reveal the the
Buddha nature it helps the Sprout to pop
out and then everybody says oh there
must have been a seed in there okay
so that's the example here
now usually there's a specific kind of
veil right we went through the three
what poisons poisons then the fourth one
was what all three in their manifest
form so now we got some we move on to a
whole different kind of veil the veil
here is called Tong pong uh I'll write
it for you
say do you
know uh those things which are
eliminated bang means eliminated by path
of seeing which is how many
things two or three two or three yeah
depending on how you present it right
what's the biggest one
obviously intellectual belief in
self-existence is a Tong Bong meaning a
negative thing which is eliminated Pang
by the Tongue by the path of seeing the
moment you see emptiness directly you
destroy the any capacity to
intellectually believe that what's going
on around you is what it seems okay um
the second one
was oh I'm sorry yeah
doubt doubt about the path doubt about
future lives things like that because
you see them directly you see your own
Bud Hood directly you're not going to
doubt anything anymore and then the last
one sort of Two and a Half
is which is
what yeah like wrong views about what
things are valid spiritual practices the
idea that um burning yourself or poking
yourself or things like that could be
very helpful in spiritual practice
um so the meat of the
fruit the Flesh of the
fruit the veil in this case is compared
to Tong pong okay the negative emotions
which are eliminated when you see
emptiness directly
okay and the idea is that it's this old
Buddhist idea that the production of the
cause of the production of the result
does what to the
cause destroys the cause Okay the
appearance of the result destroys the
cause like the Sprout would feed off the
Flesh of the right nice yeah the pit
feeds off the flesh the bigger the
Sprout gets the smaller the flesh gets
the more moments of path of seeing
you've been through the more details of
these three negative emotions are
destroyed so it's a very cool image the
the more the Sprout grows the more flesh
of the apricot under the Earth
disappears because the Sprout is living
off the nutrients of the flesh you see I
mean the Buddha is being developed
uh the more developed the Buddha gets
from the Buddha nature the more the
negativity start to shrink you know like
that it's kind of
cool there's a huge debate in in the
monastery about you
know at what point is there a sprout and
at what point you know can they really
be totally simultaneous and it's one of
the evidences for emptiness that it's
it's a contradiction you know you can't
point to the moment that one begins and
one ends at what point does the cause go
out of existence and at what point does
the result come into existence the fact
that it's so difficult to pinpoint that
is an evidence that it's being projected
by us and that it doesn't have an
external reality okay that's kind of
cool
uh I think that's all there is on this
one let me
see yeah that thing is cranky
yeah that's
it
okay do you remember the word for the
door the kind of door that the Hat yoga
pipa says you'd have on your on your
YT it came just before Dara in the
verse yeah ala Dara this one is alapala
okay just for your information that's
the small
ultimately that word turn to roof and
leaf because roofs used to be made from
leaves a small piece is broken off of a
tree so it means small but you'll get to
that next in Sans class
seven
is uh I don't think there is let me
see I think
see I think it's just a fact of
cultivation of cultivation you know and
that's the first time we've had that
here and that's you know if you had to
debate it this would be the one that
indicates that it's really Buddha nature
and not Buddha hood that we're talking
about inside of you the idea that it
must be cul
and and then it and that it the Buddha
which comes out of the Buddha nature
comes out in stages and grows out like
that
[Music]
uh for
smells
good
say uh you don't have that very
often G
it's HR right n
g um this K means clothes cloth piece of
cloth sh and Sh mean the same thing yeah
to rip something and it's on aat when
you rip a piece of cloth it goes and it
sounds
like okay uh
so and then nna means inside
and gal here doesn't mean galpo which is
King it means galwa which is Victor
which is AB Buddha Jina okay and then C
means the body Caya of a of a Buddha so
the body of a Buddha meaning a statue a
beautiful statue of a Buddha wrapped in
a tattered cloth or ripped cloth okay
and in the Sanskrit the word here here
in the Sanskrit which is what is that uh
PR means also means stinky rotten old R
falling apart you know it's like a
really bad piece of cloth so I was
thinking a mechan the rag a mechanic
would use or something like that you
know and
uh and the and the imagees of uh there's
a road there's a there's a major foot
path you know like in India between
Villages and people are coming and going
constantly and there's this right beside
the right at the side of the road
there's this Old Rag
uh sitting there and no one pays any
attention to it because they don't need
to and but inside it is a Priceless
golden image of a Buddha or something
you know and nobody nobody knows you
know so obviously you need somebody to
come along and it's Lord Buddha and they
say look you know pick it up check out
what's inside of it and then the veil is
lifted and you and you see what's
[Music]
inside galub J makes the further note
that the veil in this case
uh well I should say what the veil
represents if the last Veil which was
what fruit the meat of the fruit the you
know the outside flesh of the fruit if
that represented um what you eliminate
by seeing at the path of seeing what do
you guess this one
represents getting close yeah what you
eliminate at the path of of
habituation okay path number
four okay yeah so this in this case the
cloth represents the
negativities that you
lose uh by perfecting the fourth path
the path of
habituation uh which is actually
everything else okay which is actually
all the other obstacles okay somewhere
along path of
habituation
um and gab J says if you think about it
if you take a piece of cloth a piece of
paper and you rip it into three or four
pieces in a way it loses its
substantiality it loses its clothess in
a way at a certain point you stop
thinking of it as a piece of paper at a
certain point you stop thinking of it as
a cloth and just as the growth of the
Sprout was the cause of the destruction
of the meat of the fruit The Ripping of
the cloth of the veil uh means that it's
almost insubstantial and obviously from
there a small jump to saying the mental
afflictions that were giving you all the
trouble at the fourth path were empty
anyway they weren't substantial anyway
were they you know they weren't what you
thought they were okay so g j throws in
all that all that stuff kind of
cool oh and I wanted to say uh this
one and the one about the the Mone money
under the Earth floor or the gold what
was it gold right
treasure those two are the ones which
are most quoted in later literature
those two are the ones that you see
almost all the time in the debate
textbooks in in the monasteries
especially the one about the poor person
finding an unexpected treasure and not
even knowing it was there you see we get
the theme Here Again these two are very
big on you have that Buddha nature it
exists inside of you it's been there
since the day you were conceived or if
you believe in Buddhism for countless
lifetimes and you just never knew it was
there you know so those two are
considered the most important two the
one about the cloth and the one about
the treasure under the floor and they'd
be most likely to come up in a debate
textbook or in a quiz for
example it seems like six would come up
a lot too because it it seems to
substantiate what the difference is
between Buddha nature and Buddha hood
for us I mean we using it the most in
ACI especially in CL when we ever debate
with anybody who's jba right
or there are some very very competent
serious Scholars who believe in Jon very
strongly you know uh so it's not a small
thing to study it's important to study
and um shent this idea a different kind
of emptiness okay shent yeah it's very
good to know
tarata who wrote the history book that
we studied for ARA's life believed in it
the kis believe in it all the kagis
believe in it and en Tata took it to
Mongolia because he was the main llama
there and and so a lot of uh the a lot
of the understanding of emptiness among
many Traditions has been affected I
believe you can trace it historically
back to these nine examples just uh
because it seemed like something
substantial like you open the banana
peel in the first example and there's a
banana I mean it's not like empty it's
not like nothing's there you know uh but
gab is quite adamant that this is Buddha
nature and it's it's actually an absence
but you can't discover the absence until
you remove the veil
okay uh okay number
eight this one I think is the most sort
of uh touching
one for
[Music]
and
oh
sorry ick
here sorry
say Okay pum means a woman okay it's the
Tibetan word for a
[Music]
woman singular
yeah means bad it in this this case it
means ugly smells bad doesn't have any
money and he wearing tattered clothes
okay like a really down andout lady okay
Street lady say like a street lady yeah
like a bag lady really it's like a bag
lady okay and then to to means jatara
in's what's jar do you know
remember the Tumo really belly fire do
means belly
belly and inside the
belly this me means a person like human
being me sometimes me means negative
right but here it means it's the me that
means a person or a a human being Doc is
the doc and dobo that means owner and
mid do means the Lord of all humans and
it's a synonym for
uhak what's
that yeah a world Emperor this is
somebody whose karma is so good that
everybody in the world knocks on their
door say you know will you come be
president of the world you know like
they don't have to campaign they don't
have to fight anybody everybody in the
world unanimously is dying to have them
be king of the world and they become
king of the world they own everything in
the world they have the karma they even
get signs on them like a Buddhist signs
but they're called a Salam Mao uh means
they're in the Abid Dharma third chapter
their signs are not complete like they
start to get a wheel on their hands but
it's like indistinct and a little bit
offc Center uh but they got that much
Karma that you know a lot of times
people are faced with being uh king of
the world or hang or to hold out for
buddhahood you know like Lord atesa or
AA or Shanti DEA you know it's very
common in Buddhism for somebody to get
faced with this choice you know you can
either be a very successful businessman
and like own the corporate world
or you can sort of slow down on that and
become enlightened you know yeah yeah
faced with the riches of the world and
this is very common um in religious
literature because obviously have the
karma to almost be anything they want to
be so do are they going to step back a
bit from the from this corporate success
or are they going to you know do this
and you know I'm not saying you can't
work in a corporation I'm not saying you
can't be high up in a corporation I
can't not even saying you can't own a
corporation but what I'm saying is that
you would be the faced at some point
with with putting all your energy into
wealth or worldly success and then and
then really um it becomes a it's a
common fork in the road for Spiritual
people and then they they kind of go
this way and and go off and live in a
Europe for something like that you know
like you you know you're almost here and
you're almost like president of the
United States or something and then you
just you go that way and that's very
common so uh anyway so World Emperors
have these marks almost like a
Buddha that's mid yeah midok is a is a
word for kri galpo which is uh Chuck
ofart
um so the idea is that this bag lady has
within her belly she's
pregnant and there's the next emperor of
the world is in her belly and she
doesn't know it I mean it's not even
clear from the book is she knows she's
pregnant you know
but within her is someone who's about to
become emperor of the world and the
angle here okay the
angle is that she is unprotected she has
no one to help her like maybe she's
unmarried uh she's homeless and she has
no one to fend for her and and in and in
Ancient India this was a real problem if
you didn't have a a formal husband it
was just dangerous you know like no one
would save you from getting raped or
taking advantage of or things like that
if you didn't belong to a family if you
didn't have a husband the the the force
of law was not so strong that a woman
could be protected and so the idea is
that she's alone she doesn't have a
strong house and you know if you've seen
the Huts in India why do you think
people in India wear gold you know in
The Villages because there's no el else
to put it it has to be on your body or
it will get stolen you know anyone can
break into a straw hun and you can't
trust the banks so for hundreds and
hundreds of years people have converted
grain or everything into gold that you
could wear on your body and take it with
you out in the fields and know where it
was all day and that so she's like
defenseless she has nothing and then the
idea is that here in her belly is the
person who will become the defender of
the world like already in her belly is a
being who can defend the entire world
protect the gombo the NAT of the entire
world is in her belly and she's going to
give birth to this being and she doesn't
have any protection at all you know so
the idea the angle here is that if you
play your uh calm cards right your your
uh Buddha nature cards right then slowly
the gestation period will happen and a
Buddha will come out and then you become
protector of everybody here's everybody
with nothing here's everybody in the
world with no protection
man we went to see relatives for three
weeks in July that was all we did for
three weeks in July you know we went and
heard about who's got cancer we went and
heard about who's died we went and heard
about tons of people who lost their jobs
we went and heard about people who are
now afraid of losing their jobs and are
working like slaves like bosses must be
going crazy in this time right now you
know you know they're like I have to
work 18 hours a day well just quit I
can't get a job you know and so like
it's you know we went and then we saw
all the friends who' gotten old and
their hair is all you know don't see
somebody for 5 years or don't see
somebody for 10 years be in Retreat for
3 years and then come out like you know
it's like depressing it's really
depressing and then they hear all the
people who died you know and uh there's
no protector there's no protection they
don't have any protection it's like it's
like walking out and seeing a bunch of
kids in the middle of the desert with no
water you know it's like it's just a
matter of time you know a bunch of
one-year-old babies lying in the sand in
the desert and and you just look at them
they're not going to crawl they're going
to crawl the to buoy you know and if
they do what's going to happen
you you know so you know when it's
hopeless it's just hopeless and you meet
them and you shake hands and you have
lunch and you try to be polite and
friendly and then you say goodbye
knowing that it's just time you know
it's just a matter of time
they don't have any protection and the
protection the potential for the
protection lies within them and if they
just gestated it
properly they would produce the great
the greatest protector in the world they
would become the greatest protector in
the world they wouldn't have to worry
about someone to take care of them you
know so that's the the beauty of this
one that's the I I really like this one
I like the idea
of it's just very touching for me that
to think of
a you are pregnant already everybody in
this room is is already pregnant that's
kind of cool you know everybody in this
room is already you just have to
gestate that's kind
of yeah and and
the and the what do you call it the
uh the gradualness of the gestation they
say rimbe rimbe means step by step month
by month it will continue to grow and
then it will come out but the big angle
is protection you know
that in this case you're you're
cultivating you're gestating uh ultimate
protection for yourself and everybody
else real protection it you know it can
be quite overwhelming to go from a
three-year Retreat to um eating dinner
uh next to a bar in um what's that place
Universal Studios with five different
video uh things going on above the bar
and a live band playing and uh
no and and a bowl behind you uh the
mechanical bowl with people screaming
and then they come out with a
yes they come out with a they come out
with a two a 1x 12 board like a 3T 1x12
board piled with french fries for one
person to eat you know and then you just
like and she gets all gray she got all
gray and she's going to pass out you
know and I'm like don't pass out you
know and uh and and then just to look
around and and the woman who took us
there at just before we get out of her
car she says wait wait I just want to
ask you you did this three treat thing
right yeah well my father died a few
weeks ago and my brother died a few
weeks before that can you help me you
know is there anything you could tell me
you know like we survived this whole
dinner thinking what why are we here you
know and then but it's protection you
know there's no protection there's
nothing you know I mean she was like
very interested in three Retreat cuz she
had what we call nin and pusses say n
it means U Goosebump uh Goosebump
renunciation like okay for six weeks
she'll she'll be real interested and
then it'll start to wear off you know
because it's not based on knowledge it's
just based on a terrible experience that
she
had um so anyway there we get uh
protection last
one oh that represents my
so we're still on number eight yeah I'm
sorry this is the nature of the
veil which was I guess the the woman and
her clothing and her environment which
are misleading in a way you can't you
know they this is a veil like her
appearance the mother the body of the
mother of the poor impoverished uh mag
lady is a veil and then the the the
child inside is like the Buddha nature
right and the idea is that in this case
the veil is mad say
mad mapa means uh impure not pure and
then sa means levels like bodh Safa
boomies it's the boomi bodh Safa Bui
okay the impure bodh Safa
levels when you do the practice of
trying to perceive everyone in your
world and your world as pure as per what
V 140 but he not it's not my favorite I
didn't know it was 140 I guess it's 140
but um my favorite it's my favorite uh
even before Tantra I mean this is an
open B right that's called Dak Nang the
main practice is called Dak Nang where
you try to see everything is to so mad
means impure the first seven bisfa
levels are called mad impure levels the
first seven of the 10 bodh sappa levels
bodh sappa bomis are called impure
because you still have grasping to
self-existence and its uh gross seeds
Okay in fact when you reach bodh SATA
level number
eight you've achieved what uh relative
to lower path
it's Nirvana because you got rid of the
last tendency of seeing things as
self-existent okay so those are called
impure levels gross level yeah okay so
these are called the mother the dirty
mother the poor ugly mother is is
compared the veil is compared to these
to all the obstacles in the first seven
bodh levels all the obstacles all the
mental afflictions all the problems in
the first seven bodh sappa levels which
are mainly to do with what
grasping at self exist grasping at
things as being self-existent all of
those Tendencies are compared to the
mother's body okay the bag lady is the
first sub yeah yeah and these are all
coming from gz up day like he's
researched the sutras and he gives it to
you it's really hard to find otherwise
okay the the nature of the veil in each
case Okay number nine
okay for
say Salah
Salah Salah
sal sal means in Earth which in this
case means in mud or in clay
okay Ren means precious like rot right
um
and it can mean Jewel but it can also
mean gold or silver like all those are
called renin gold Sil precious metals
and precious stones are all referred to
as Ren in Tibetan or
Roch Suk means uh form or statue in this
case it means a statue so a Buddha
statue made of jewels and gold
um sort of covered with with a thin
layer of veneer veneer is a very good
weird word here veneer a veneer of
clay uh or what
terracotta might be a good word but the
idea is you you look at this statue and
it looks like it's made of clay
terracotta but 1 millimeter below the
surface is a pure gold you know statue
with with jewels on it and like that
okay and the idea is that look you can
still recognize that it's what
a Buddha right I mean it still looks
like a Buddha right and it's just this
little veneer this little subtle
covering of something
impure so if the veil in the last in
number eight was the first seven or the
impure bodh Safa boomies what's the veil
in number
nine yeah bodh Safa levels eight nine
and 10 which collectively are called
Daka D just take the ma off the last one
okay these are called the pure
levels in bodh Safi levels 8 9 and 10
you no longer are seeing things that
self-existent and you don't have grow
seeds for doing that you still have so
you've reached nirvana in a way okay but
you still have uh very subtle subtle
Tendencies and you still have uh what we
call Mishi which is uh obstacles to to
reaching omniscience itself so there's a
difference between polishing off your
last bad emotion
and then having your mind open to where
you can see every object in the universe
at the same time like there's a
distinction there right get rid of your
last jealousy angry anger hatred is one
thing being able to see what's going on
on the other side of Pluto right now on
a certain Speck of dust is a different
thing so uh the impurities here the
obstacles here the veil here is very
tble tble means thin subtle easy to I
mean not a big deal anymore
it's just a veneer okay the veil is like
a veneer now and not a it's not going to
be a major problem to get it off you
know you just get a cloth and you wipe
it off and that's the the thing is
finished okay so the last one is the
most hopeful one anyway right let me see
if he says anything
else yeah it's just that that by this
time you're pretty aware of the
veil okay by this time it's not a big
it's not like totally hidden from the
Buddha nature is not like something out
of your league by now you can obviously
see that there's a Buddha under the
veneer okay so that's the last
one so I'd like to repeat from
here uh we go to
a we go to a discussion of what is the
Buddha nature like you know here we've
been almost concentrating on the
veils and because of this presentation
it's beginning to feel to you like
what's concealed by the veil is
something solid concrete a positive
thing so you almost start to get that uh
jungian feel that there's
uh something concrete beneath the veil
you know beneath the clay beneath the
veneer and so the job in the next class
is to go back to the C textbooks which
are the same among all the great
monasteries I mean they all say the same
thing uh to discover what is uh what is
Buddha nature you see what is it
really uh okay these uh all these veils
are called lur Kima say lour
l Chima Chim lour means temporary
removable okay nothing innate like all
of these veils are something you can get
rid of and then when you get rid of them
you can reveal Buddha nature and the
process of getting rid of them creates a
Buddha from the Buddha nature okay so
next class uh which will be class number
what seven we got to talk about what is
bua nature and we're going to do that
with dialectic again you know there'll
be a debates you know a lot of debates
and then we'll get to the wrong laka
which is okay this is what Buddha nature
really is
emptiness establishing that Buddha
nature really refers to your personal
emptiness okay then in the eighth class
the the third class this month um we'll
go into it'll be like I'll change hats
right and I'll be a jungan and I'll be
giving you our presentation of why those
gukas are wrong you know why Buddha
nature can't be just some absence of
something you
know nine nine images I mean you know
it's not like
you the the has nothing in her womb you
know what are you thinking what's wrong
with you you know it's a potential it's
a positive energy it's a seed and that
happens to be the mind only schools idea
also you see uh so we'll be looking at
it uh from both points of view you'll
get like mind only classical mind only
presentations that also support this
idea and I think it's very good just for
advanced uh Dharma discussions with
people like there might be three people
in the country who understand your
number Viewpoint well and if you ever
meet them you can uh debate with them or
something they'll call be in Tucson yeah
well what I mean is in my class in your
class there're sort of a well if you
prepar they won't be right but um but
there's sort of this thing where great
historical debates are based on natural
problems that all of us would have in
our thinking you know that's the why the
Jonas who are really Buddhas
uh turn that turning of the wheel they
want us to think about it they want us
to thrash it out they want us to wonder
who's right because by um through the
process of uh agonizing over whether uh
ziles has the best diamonds or uh bbnb
has the best diamonds you will what no
you'll buy a diamond you see so if the
guy is smart he'll open up both stores
in one mall and then he'll start a
raging debate over are the jonian right
or the Galas right you know and then in
the process all of us plain old Schmucks
will learn
emptiness uh so we believe that you know
all the different it's like Chong right
uh obviously those great llamas are not
fools and obviously they know what
emptiness is but by engaging in this
giant uh
acting what drama
play uh where they attack each other you
know uh you know where great llamas
getting controversies then um they force
their disciples to come to a clear
understanding of a point and and that's
very common in debate and very common in
the way that llamas uh do things and and
that and Lord Buddha started all these
debates also among the four classical
schools of Buddhism so it's just a tbk
uh which means
what we found a new translation whatever
works yeah if you think about it
whatever works is not bad okay so the
Suk in Sal refers to this Suk means uh
body in the sense of a of a statue okay
but it refers to it's a metaphor for
nature not yeah well according to us us
yes they would say Buddha nature is
buddhahood yeah right the debate yeah
yeah that'll be this big debate and
we'll attack
them
vociferously and
voraciously okay okay uh we'll stop
we're going to run away for a while and
take a break uh and uh then we'll have
dinner together okay we can hang out and
have dinner
okay for
[Music]
happy
turning h